Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer papers
1897-1968
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer
8.5 linear feet
The papers of painter, printmaker, and photographer Konrad Cramer and his wife, painter and printmaker Florence Ballin Cramer, measure 8.5 linear feet and date from 1897 to 1968. Papers document both artists' personal and professional lives and are especially rich in documentation of the art community of Woodstock, NY, where Florence Ballin first attended art classes in 1906, and where the couple settled in 1911. Records include biographical materials, correspondence, a Christmas card album, writings, business records, personal financial records, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.
Biographical Note
Konrad Cramer was born in Wurtzburg, Germany, in 1888, and studied at the Karlsruhe Academy of Fine Arts from 1906 to 1908 with Ludwig Schmidt-Reutte and Ernest Schurth. After a year in the German army, he returned to Karlsruhe to set up a studio, making frequent trips to Munich, where he was exposed to the experimental artists of the Blaue Reiter group, including Wassily Kandinsky and Franz Marc.
Florence Ballin was born in Brooklyn, NY, in 1884. She studied at the Woodstock, New York, summer school of the Art Students League beginning in 1906 under Birge Harrison along with fellow students John Carlson, Grace Mott Johnson, and Andrew Dasburg. She served as secretary for the League in 1906, and had a studio on 59th Street in Manhattan, where she held her first exhibition in 1909. In 1911, she traveled to Europe and met Konrad Cramer in Munich and joined him on visits to exhibitions and studios of the vanguard artists. The two married, moved to the United States, and settled permanently in Woodstock, NY.
Konrad Cramer is often credited as being in important link between German and American modernism in art, and his experimentations with abstraction and expressionism during his first years in Woodstock would seem to bear this out. In 1912 and 1913, he painted a series he called "Improvisations" (after Kandinsky) which was shown in a group exhibition at the MacDowell Club in 1913 along with Andrew Dasburg, Oliver Chaffee, and Paul Rohland. Cramer was photographed by Alfred Stieglitz and wrote an essay about the 291 Gallery for Stieglitz's magazine, Camera Work, in 1914.
The Cramers had two daughters, in 1914 and 1917, and Konrad Cramer became an American citizen in 1917. For income, he began designing textiles for department stores using stencils and batiks around 1918. In his painting, he turned from abstract experiments to the traditional subjects of landscape, still life, and figure in a more representational style that blended modern and regional influences. Florence Ballin Cramer opened a gallery on 57th Street in 1919, encouraged by the sculptor Elie Nadelman. The mission of the Florence Gallery, as it was called, was to exhibit and sell the work of living artists. Although it only survived the season, it was the first gallery to show work by Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Alexander Brook, Ernest Fiene, and Stefan Hirsch, and generated important sales for several young artists in her circle.
Konrad Cramer returned to Europe in 1920 on a Rockefeller grant to study educational methods for craftsmen in Germany and France, and on his return he taught at the Woodstock School of Painting and Allied Arts. Cramer also studied lithography with Bolton Brown in Woodstock around this time, and both Cramers took up printmaking and began publishing prints in local arts magazines. The Cramers were deeply immersed in Woodstock life, participating in the annual Maverick festivals, the Woodstock Artists Association, the Historical Society, and other organizations, hosting meetings and serving as officers of many committees and organizations that presented and supported artwork in their community. They enjoyed a rich social life there among fellow artists at frequent parties and festivals, where Konrad provided entertainment with his fiddle and both Cramers memorialized events in countless photographs.
Konrad Cramer exhibited at the Whitney Studio Club in 1924, and taught at the Children's University School (now the Dalton School), where he painted a mural in 1929. The 1930s were busy years in both Cramers' professional lives. Konrad's exhibitions included the Carnegie International (1929 and 1933), and a two-man show at the Dudensing Gallery (1930), where Cramer and Adolph Gottlieb had been selected the most deserving unknown American painters of the year. He was also included in the exhibit Abstract Painting in America at the Whitney Museum (1935). Florence Ballin Cramer exhibited at Marie Harriman Gallery (1931 and 1933), Macy Galleries (1933), at the Pennsylvania Academy (1934 and 1936), and the Corcoran (1935 and 1937). Both Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer were included in a traveling exhibition of Woodstock artists organized by the College Art Association (1931), the first and second Whitney Biennials (1933 and 1935), and the Wanamaker Regional Art Exhibition of Contemporary American Painting (1934).
In 1934, the Cramers traveled to Mexico, where they produced many paintings and drawings. Konrad Cramer joined the Federal Art Project briefly in 1935, administering the regional program in Woodstock with Judson Smith. It was around this time that he began to learn photography. He became a sort of community photographer, taking photographs of friends' artwork and commissioned portraits, as well as informal photographs of friends. Cramer experimented with photographic techniques such as solarization and collage, using prisms, panes of glass, or composite printing. He first exhibited photographs in 1936 at the Albany Institute, and established the Woodstock School of Miniature Photography (the "miniature" referring to the then-new format of 35mm film) in 1937. He also taught courses in photography at Bard College in the 1940s, and his photographs and articles about photography were published in national magazines.
For the remainder of his life, Cramer continued to teach, write, and produce photographs, occasionally returning to painting, drawing, and printmaking, creating gouaches, wax resist drawings, and stencils of landscapes and figures, with an increasing interest in abstract styles and automatic techniques. Three of his early paintings were included in the 1946 Whitney Museum exhibition Pioneers of Modern Art in America, and the same year, he exhibited abstract photographs at the Woodstock Artists Association. In the late 1940s, he built an automatic drawing machine which he called the sympalmagraph, which rendered precise, geometric forms. In the late 1950s, he collaborated on a traveling exhibition and book of abstract photographs with Manuel Komroff and Nathan Resnik called The Third Eye.
Florence Ballin Cramer held her last exhibitions at the Woodstock Town House gallery (1953) and at Long Island University (1957). She died in 1962. Konrad Cramer died the following year. Both were memorialized in an exhibition at the Woodstock Artists Association Gallery in 1968.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, printmaker, and photographer Konrad Cramer and his wife, painter and printmaker Florence Ballin Cramer, measure 8.5 linear feet and date from 1897 to 1968. Papers document both artists' personal and professional lives and are especially rich in documentation of the art community of Woodstock, NY, from 1906, when Florence first attended art classes there, and where the couple resided until their deaths in the 1960s. Records include biographical materials, correspondence, a Christmas card album, business records, writings, personal financial records, printed materials, photographs, and artwork.
Correspondence is between the Cramers and other artists, curators, gallery staff, editors, writers, and personal friends and family. Many drafts and carbons of outgoing letters are also present. The Christmas card album brings together original cards made by their artist friends in the 1920s and early 1930s. Writings include diaries of both artists, mostly from 1949 onward, with notes and excerpts from earlier diaries present; technical and biographical essays by Konrad Cramer, and autobiographical and historical essays by Florence Ballin Cramer; notebooks and notes related to art, travel, photography, and other subjects. Personal Business Records include price lists, receipts, and gallery correspondence with dealers and exhibitors; correspondence, accounting records, and writings related to Florence Ballin Cramer's Florence Gallery in New York City (1919-1920); records related to Woodstock arts and civic organizations in which the Cramers were involved; and personal financial records.
Printed Materials include publicity materials related to the Cramers' various endeavors and the activities of Woodstock arts and civic organizations, as well as dozens of books, little magazines, and journals by and about members of the Woodstock artist's colony. Photographs depict the Cramers and their friends, including early Art Students League Classes and the annual Maverick festival in the 1920s. Also found are a small number of photo-collages and experiments with color photography, and a series of early twentieth century photographs in the pictorialist style. Artwork includes early sketchbooks of both artists; loose sketches, drawings, and designs; textile designs by Konrad Cramer; and prints and printing blocks.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1898-1955 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1900-1964 (Boxes 1-3, 9; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Christmas Card Album, 1921-1961 (Box 3, 0.8 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1897-1962 (Boxes 4-5, 11; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 5: Personal Business Records, 1918-1962 (Boxes 5, 10; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Materials, 1906-1968 (Boxes 6-7, 11; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1906-1960 (Box 7; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Artwork, 1897-1954 (Boxes 8-11; 1.2 linear feet)
Separated Material
Originals of loaned material, including diaries (Florence Ballin Cramer, 1917-1920; Konrad Cramer, 1918-1921), sketches, and photographs, were returned to Aileen Cramer after microfilming. Loaned material is available for viewing on microfilm reels D170-D171 and 1027, but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Index to Selected Correspondence in Series 2
This index to Konrad and Florence Ballin Cramer's Correspondence in Series 2 includes selected artists, curators, dealers, patrons, neighbors, and other significant correspondents. Illustrated letters and significant enclosures are indicated in parentheses. This index is not comprehensive.
Apple, Marianne: 1942-1943
Bacon, Peggy: 1922-1924, 1930, 1940, 1942, undated
Barkin, Maeluise; 1950, 1962
Barrère, George: 1932
Barrère, Jean: 1950
Bartlett, Mabel: 1957-1958
Berkowitz, Sidney: 1954
Bieber, Alfred: 1952, 1958, 1963, undated
Blashfield, Edwin Howland: 1906
Bloch, Julius: 1937, undated
Boch, Alfred: 1961
Boissevain Nusbaum, Anne: 1942, 1950, 1960, 1962
Bourgeois, Stephan: 1924
Braun, Alfred: 1957, 1959-1960, 1962-1963
Bridgeman, George: 1906
Brook, Alexander: 1924-1927, 1930
Bullard, Marion: 1939, 1949
Cahill, Holger: 1934
Campbell, Blanche: 1948-1950, 1957, 1960
Carlson, John: 1909-1911, 1913
Carlson, Margaret (Mrs. John): 1962-1963
Chambers, Faith: undated
Chase, Barbara: 1947
Chase, Cathy: 1947
Cohn, Hilda: 1949
Cowell, Sidney: 1962
Cox, Kenyon: 1906
Cramer, Belle: 1954
Dasburg, Andrew: 1909, 1921, 1924-1927, 1931, 1945, 1955, 1959, undated
Davenport, John: 1951-1953, 1955, 1963
Delden, Gisela van: 1911, 1927, 1938-1939, 1952, 1954, 1956-1960
DeLiagre, Alfred, Ally, and Delly: 1935, 1937, 1942-1943, 1948-1949, 1952, 1958, 1960, undated
Dexter, Lindsay: 1939-1940
Dickens, Elsa: 1962
Dudensing, Leroy: undated
Dudensing, Richard: 1932
DuFrène, Mary: undated
DuMond, Frank Vincent: 1906
Dunbar, Henry: 1962
Dunn, R. Loring; 1935-1937
Eidlitz, Dorothy Meigs: 1945-1951, 1959-1960, 1962
Evans, Grace: 1924, 1930 (photos enclosed), 1932, 1940, 1942, 1956, undated
Ficke, Evelyn: undated
Fischer, Anton Otto: 1943
Force, Juliana: 1921, 1932-1934, 1936
Fortess, Karl: 1935, 1940, 1945-1947, 1954, 1962
Fortess, Lillian: 1934-1935, 1958
Franklin, George: 1933
Ganso, Emil: 1940-1941
Ganso, Fanny: 1941-1947, 1949, 1951, undated
George, Rowland: undated
George, Thomas: 1963
Gershoy (Gottlieb), Eugenie: 1927, 1937
Gise, Margaret: 1934
Gittis, Archie: 1929, 1939, undated
Goldberg, Rube: 1937 (illustrated)
Goodrich, Lloyd: 1962-1963
Grant, Stuart: 1945
Grosz, George: 1933, 1939
Guggenheim, Mrs. Jules: 1959
Guinzburg, Liu: 1941, undated
Gurewitsch, Arno D.: 1936-1937, undated
Harrison, Birge: 1910
Hartman, Gusta and Bertram: 1928
Haz, Hicholas: 1941
Henderson, Alice: 1947
Hermann, Norbert: 1962
Hervey, Wilna: 1931, 1934-1938, 1940-1941, 1951(illustrated), 1956 (illustrated), 1962, undated (photos enclosed)
Johnson, Grace Mott: 1910, 1911, 1916-1918, 1921, 1947
Jones, Jane (Mrs. Wendell): 1956
Karasz, Ilonka: undated (original print)
Kass, Marie: 1957-1959
Kessel, Therese Woodleaf: 1957
Kleinert, Hermine "Mousie": 1911, 1919-1924, 1931-1934, 1936-1941, undated
Klitgaard, Georgia: 1911, 1913-1914, 1946, undated
Komroff, Manuel: 1945-1946, 1949-1952, 1956-1957, 1959-1961, 1963, undated
Krom, Alice: 1935, 1943-1944, 1957
Kuniyoshi, Katherine: 1956
Kuniyoshi, Sara: 1954
Labrot, Elanor: 1935
Langner, Lawrence: 1920
Lathrop, Charles: 1937, undated
Lester, Henry: 1945, 1952-1956, undated
Lester, Janka: 1940, 1942-1944, 1946, 1949, 1951, 1955-1956, 1958, 1963
Lindin, Greg: 1944-1945, undated
Lindin, Carl Eric: 1934
Lindin, Louise: 1962
Marsh, Fred Dana: 1944, 1948-1949, 1953, 1956
Marshall, James: 1953, 1955-1956
Marshall, Lenore: 1941, 1953, 1955-1958, 1963
Mason, Nan: see Wilna Hervey
Mayer, Grace: 1959-1960
Mayers, Martha: 1934, 1945, 1950, 1953
McFee, Aileen: 1917, 1919, 1921, 1928, 1930-1937, 1941, undated
McFee, Henry Lee: 1921-1922, 1930-1931, 1935, 1951, undated
Meadows, Harriet: 1962
Mearns, Bill Hughes and Fagley: 1935, 1938-1939, 1941, 1949, 1956
Mecklem, Austin "Meck" and Marianne: 1950, 1959
Michelson, Nancy: 1959-1960
Miles, Florence: 1949
More, Herman; 1935, 1944
Nadelman, Elie: 1914, undated
Nadelman, Viola: 1925-1927, 1942, 1948-1949, undated
Nelson, Doris Starr: undated (poems enclosed)
Neuman, Janet: 1933-1935, 1956, 1960, 1962
Neuman, Robert: 1959
Niggli, Josefina and G. Morgan: 1935, 1938-1939, 1942, 1948
Nusbaum, Dorothy: 1943, undated
Obendorf, C.P.: 1945, 1952
Oberferst, Norman: 1955
Oertel, Curt: 1953
Offner, Phillipa Whiting: 1942
Ostes, Camela: 1934-1935, 1938
Ottenberg, Irving: 1908, 1959, undated
Ottenberg, Reuben: 1917, 1934, 1939, 1942-1945, 1948-1949, 1951, 1953, 1957, 1959, undated (photo enclosed)
Pachner, Bill and Lorraine: 1945-1946, 1950, 1956, 1959, undated
Parkhurst, Helen: 1933
Penning, Tom: 1943-1944
Pittman, Hobson: 1931, 1934, 1940
Polansky, Ed: 1958-1959
Pollard, William; 1954
Ransohoff, Danny: 1943-1947, 1949-1953
Reilly, Mary: 1911, 1921
Resnick, Nat: 1957, 1962, 1963, undated
Riesberg, Sid: undated
Riley, Charlotte: 1923, undated
Rohland, Caroline Speare: 1932-1933, 1942-1944, 1947, 1949, 1952, 1954, 1959, 1963, undated
Rohland, Paul: undated
Rollo, Jo: 1928-1930
Saint-Gaudens, Carlota: 1911, undated
Saint-Gaudens, Homer: 1923, 1919, 1933, 1937
Segal, Bill: 1953
Shermund, Barbara: 1939, 1942, undated
Schultz, Andi: 1931-1933, undated
Siegel, Adrian and Sophie: 1943-1944, 1953, undated
Simonson, Lee: 1921, 1932-1933, undated
Sluizer, Esther: 1951, 1962
Slusser, Jean Paul: 1933
Smith, Frank Leon: 1931, 1958, 1962-1963
Smith, Judson: 1934-1935
Sortwell, Frances: 1948
Speicher, Gene: 1927, 1929 (photo enclosed), undated
Sprinchorn, Carl: undated
Stieglitz, Alfred: 1916, 1921
Streibel, J.H.: 1956 (illustrated)
Summers, Dudley: 1950-1953, 1955
Trafton, Howard: 1926-1927
Uhlenhutt, Edward "Uhli": 1918, 1919, 1921, 1927, 1935, 1937-1938, 1940-1942, 1945, 1947-1952, 1954-1959
Varian, Dorothy: 1944
Vaughn, Hilda: 1940, undated
Walters, Carl: 1948
Wangler, Albert: 1962
Watson, Forbes: 1938-1939
Watson, Thomas Jr.: 1958
Webster, Ben: undated
Wehle, Harry B.: 1921-1922, 1944
Weyhe, E.: 1927
White, Hervey: undated
Wilson, Marty and Dave: 1952, 1957, 1959-1960, 1962
Wingate, Bill and Maxine: 1962
Wolfman, Gus: 1959-1960
Zimm, Louise: 1962
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Woodstock Artists Association (Woodstock, N.Y.)
Subjects-Topical:
Artist colonies -- New York (State) -- Woodstock; Festivals; Painters -- New York (State) -- Woodstock; Photographers -- New York (State); Printmakers -- New York (State) -- Woodstock
Types of Materials:
Christmas cards; Photographs; Diaries
Names:
Cramer, Florence Ballin, 1884-1962
Provenance
A portion of the papers in this collection were loaned to the Archives of American Art for microfilming in 1964 by Aileen Cramer and Margot Cramer Taylor, daughters of Florence and Konrad Cramer. Selected diaries, sketches, and photographs were returned to Aileen Cramer at that time. Some, but not all, of the original loan was subsequently donated, along with additional materials, in 1975. Materials returned to the donor can be viewed on microfilm.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research.
Alternative Forms Available
Microfilm of much of the collection is available on microfilm reels D170-D171, 1027, 1203-1204, 2751-2757 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Materials, 1898-1955, undated, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Biographical materials include a birth certificate for Konrad Cramer; picture postcards showing views of Konrad Cramer's neighborhood in Karlsruhe, Germany; the calling card of the man who introduced Konrad and Florence; the Cramers' wedding announcement; a biographical essay about Konrad Cramer; an informal will written by Florence Ballin Cramer; and other personal certificates and documents.
  Items in this series were previously scattered throughout the collection. Most can be viewed on reels 2751, 2755, and 2756.
  - Biographical Materials, 1898-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1900-1964, undated, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3, 9; 2.2 linear feet)
  This series consists of Florence Ballin Cramer and Konrad Cramer's correspondence, including outgoing drafts and carbons of letters written by the Cramers. Correspondence is arranged chronologically, with undated letters and drafts of letters filed alphabetically at the end of the series. Before 1911 correspondence is entirely that of Florence Ballin, and the letters of 1911 are dominated by a large volume of letters between Florence Ballin and Konrad Cramer during the months of their courtship, many of which are in German. Letters and notes between the two are found throughout the series. Also found are letters to Florence's brother Irving Ballin, and letters to and from the Cramer's children, Margot and Aileen. An increasing number of outgoing drafts of letters written by Konrad Cramer are found beginning in the 1950s.
  Correspondents include artists, curators, gallery staff, editors, writers, and personal friends and family. Artists represented here include John Carlson, Birge Harrison, Peggy Bacon, Alexander Brook, Andrew Dasburg, Alfred Stieglitz, Julius Bloch, Grace Mott Johnson, George Franklin, Hermine Kleinert, Holger Cahill, Grace Evans, Emil Ganso, George Grosz, Carl Eric Lindin, Fred Dana Marsh, Henry Lee McFee, Elie Nadelman, Homer Saint-Gaudens, Lee Simonson, Gene Speicher, Carl Sprinchorn, Alfred Stieglitz, Dorothy Varian. Artwork found in the correspondence includes a hand-painted card from Peggy Bacon and Alexander Brook (1923), a Rube Goldberg cartoon (1937), and an illustrated letter from Konrad to Florence Cramer (1957). See the index to correspondence for additional illustrated letters, and the Christmas Card album in Series 3 for additional hand-made cards.
  The correspondence files include fragments of letters, especially drafts of outgoing letters, and enclosures such as receipts, photographs, and clippings. These include early photographs of Konrad Cramer in the 1911 letters, and a photograph of Eugene Speicher from 1929. Notes made retrospectively by Florence Ballin Cramer are sometimes found with letters or on accompanying envelopes.
  Correspondence in this series is from two separate accessions which were previously microfilmed on reels D170-171 and 2751-2753, and which are now merged into a single chronological sequence. Materials that relate to galleries and exhibitions, which were formerly arranged and microfilmed with general correspondence on reels D170-171, have been moved to Personal Business Records. Scattered papers which are not correspondence, but which were interfiled with letters in the microfilm arrangement, have been relocated to their appropriate series, such as Writings, Photographs, and Printed Materials.
  Additional correspondence can be found in Personal Business Records, and drafts of outgoing letters are found in Notebooks in the Writings series. See also the Christmas Card Album for additional notes and cards. See the index to correspondence for names and dates of selected correspondants in this series.
  - Correspondence, 1900-1941, (53 folders; see also Box 9, sol) (Box 1, Folder 2-54)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1964, (36 folders; see also Box 9, sol) (Box 2, Folder 1-36)
  - Correspondence; Cramer, Aileen, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence; Cramer, Florence Ballin, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence; Cramer, Konrad, undated, (2 folders; see also Box 9, sol) (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - Correspondence; A-W, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 41-44)
  - Correspondence; First Names Only or Illegible, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, Envelopes, 1909-1963, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Oversized Correspondence, (See Box 1, f22; Box 2, f22, 25, 26, 31, and 40) (Box 9 (sol))
- Christmas Card Album, 1921-1931, 1940, 1961, undated, Series 3:; (Box 3; 0.8 linear feet)
  The Cramers' Christmas card album is a large scrapbook containing handmade cards, wrapping papers, and a collection of postcards and clippings depicting animals. Most of the Christmas cards were received between 1921 and 1931, and many bear original works of art. Artists represented in the album include Peggy Bacon, Austin Mecklem, Frank Chase, Nan Mason, Hermine Kleinert, Harry Gottlieb, Felix Payant, E. Weyhe, Cecil Chichester, Henry Lee McFee, Arthur Young, Rudolph Wetterau, Sam Wylie, Wanda Gág, Will Shuster, Judson Smith, Elsa Milius, Louise Hellstrom, Jok Billings, Henry Billings, Emil Ganso, Marisha Karasz, Lee Simonson, Jo Cantine, Carl Lindin, Orville Peets, Paul and Caroline Rohland, C. Bertram Hartman, and Peter Juley. Photographs include a portrait of Aileen and Henry Lee McFee and several photographs of friends' homes.
  Loose items found in the album which do not appear to have been pasted in originally have been removed to a separate folder. Items which were pasted in and have since become unglued have been kept in the album between the pages of what appears to be their original location.
  Additional hand-made cards are scattered throughout the Correspondence series. A small portion of cards in the album have been microfilmed on reel 2753.